Register of the Charles Hill Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Increment received in 1992 (Box 52)
  - Stanford Years file (Box 85)
    - Subject file
      - Foreign relations
        - "United States and the Defense of the Western Hemisphere, 1915-1940," Historical Scholarship in the United States by W. Holt, 1967
        - Course outlines for political science classes, Stanford University, 1990
        - "United States in the World Political Economy, 1776-1860," Associative American Development
        - "Hare in the Moon," Indian fable
        - Selected letters from Letters of the Lewis and Clark Expedition
        - Printed matter
        - "American Negotiators" by James Hutson
        - Yassir Arafat statement in Geneva, December 14, 1988
        - George Shultz statement, December 15, 1988
        - "Glassboro: Johnson Summit" by W. W. Rostow
        - "American Ambassador," Peace and the Rest of the World
        - Secret Instructions to the Chinese Army, April 25, 1961
        - Peking's View of the Ambassadorial Talks, 1968-69
        - Text of U.S.-Chinese Communique, New York Times, February 28, 1972
        - "Rating Presidents and Diplomats in Chief," by Elmer Plischke, Presidential Studies Quarterly
        - "Signals and Noise: The Intelligence Picture" by Roberta Wohlstetter, Pearl Harbor: Warning and Decision
        - "Intelligence and Foreign Policy: A Review Essay" by Robert Jervis, International Security, Winter 1986-87
      - Fundamentalism (Box 87)
        - "When Gush Comes to Shove" by Moshe Halbertal, New Republic, March 23, 1992
        - "Musawi's Game" by Martin Kramer, New Republic, March 23, 1992
        - "World On Fire with Faith" by Rosemary Ruether, New York Times Book Review, January 26, 1992
        - Printed matter
      - Gorbachev, Mikhail.
      - History
        - "Scowl of Minerva" by Stephen Holmes, review of End of History and the Last Man by Francis Fukuyama, New Republic, March 23, 1992
        - "Professor Hegel Goes to Washington" by Alan Ryan, review of End of History and the Last Man by Francis Fukuyama, New York Review of Books, March 26, 1992
        - "Collected Essays" by Raymond Aron, excerpt
      - International negotiation.
        Case studies
      - Informatics dispute - U.S.-Brazil
      - Iraq-Kuwait War.
        See Persian Gulf War, 1991
      - Israel
        - Letter of assurance to Israel, September 16, 1991
        - Letter of assurance to the Palestinians, October 18, 1991
        - History and religion.
          Charles Hill notes and excerpt from the Bible
      - Media.
      - Middle East
        - Printed matter
        - Hoover Institution, including memoranda and Charles Hill notes
        - War to peace, including printed matter, Charles Hill notes and manuscript
        - Peace process
          - Speech by Charles Hill
          - Drafts by Charles Hill
        - Peace negotiations (Sol Linowitz)
      - Military power.
        Paper by Peter Paret
      - Moscow coup, August 19-21, 1991
        - Charles Hill notes
        - "Meaning of the Failed Coup," remarks to Bechtel partners by George Shultz, August 22, 1991
        - Draft treaty on the Union of Sovereign States, July 1991
        - Copy of letter to Eduard Shevardnadze from George Shultz, August 19, 1991
        - Correspondence with Tom Campbell's office, August 1991
        - Printed matter
      - Nationalism
        - Excerpts, Myth of the Nation and the Vision of Revolution by J. L. Talmon
        - "With All Her Faults, She's My Country Still," Economist, December 22, 1990
        - "Origins of Israeli Political Culture" by Myron Aronoff
        - "Be Nice to the Germans," New York Times, 1990
        - "Obstinate or Obsolete?" by Stanley Hoffmann
        - "Past and Future of Nationalism in China" by Joseph Levenson
        - "National Crowd Symbols," chapter from Crowds and Power by Elias Canetti
        - "Historical Basis for National Autonomy," Structure of Nations and Empires by Reinhold Niebuhr
        - "Ethno-Centrifugal Force" by William Safire, New York Times, June 25, 1990
        - "Now It's the Ukraine's Turn" by Adrian Karatnycky, Wall Street Journal, July 17, 1990
        - "Problem of Confederate Nationalism," Creation of Confederate Nationalism by Drew Faust
        - "Representing China" paper by Arthur Waldron, June 1990
        - "Nation-States and Multinational States," Nationalism by Peter Alter
        - "Internationalism versus Cosmopolitanism," Ideas in Conflict by Edward Burns
        - Printed matter
      - New World Order
        - Charles Hill notes
        - "'New World Order' Revisited," draft by Gidon Gottlieb, March 1, 1992
    - "Toward the Post-Cold War World" by John Gaddis, Foreign Affairs, undated
      - "Future World Disorder" by Daniel Bell, Winding Passage, 1980
        - Printed matter
      - North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO) (Box 88)
        - "NATO Summit and Beyond," report of the Center for Strategic & International Studies, 1994
        - Printed matter
      - Persian Gulf War, 1991
        - Charles Hill notes
        - "Letter from Washington," New Yorker, February 4, 1991
        - Outline on Persian Gulf by Harold Saunders
      - Planet
        - "Perspective" by William Walker III, Diplomatic History, Spring 1988
        - "Drug Control and the Issue of Culture in American Foreign Relations" by William Walker III, Diplomatic History, undated
        - "Building, Dwelling, Thinking," Poetry, Language, Thought, undated
        - "Curse of Legalism" by C. Krauthammer, New Republic, November 6, 1989
        - "Beyond the Study of War" by Quincy Wright, World Order Theorists, undated
        - "Geopolitical Perspectives," Geopolitical Foundations of a World Divided by Saul Cohen, 1973
        - "Evolution of Geopolitics," Geopolitics in Principle and Practice, by R. Fifield and G. Etzel Pearcy, 1944
        - Printed matter
      - Political risk
        - Henry Kissinger on trip to China, November 28, 1989
        - Charles Hill notes
        - "Case of the China Diary" by Alan Webber, Harvard Business Review, November-December 1989
        - Printed matter
        - Charles Hill notes
        - "Country Risk: Social and Cultural Aspects"
        - Two pages from Herodotus, The History
        - Correspondence, George Shultz to Roger Smith
        - "Using and Understanding the Analysis," Harvard Business Review, July-August, 1984
        - "Futures That Have Already Happened" by Peter Drucker, Economist, October 21, 1989
        - "Assessing Political Risk and National Controls," Risk Forecasting
        - "M-Factor in American History" by G. Pierson, American Quarterly, undated
        - "Ideology and National Comparative Advantage," outline
        - "Ideology and Country Analysis" by George Lodge, Ideology and National Competitiveness, 1986
        - Introduction to book by George Matthews
        - "Overview of Political Risk Assessment," Political Risk Assessment
        - Information for talk by Charles Hill to a Stanford University class entitled "Management of International Business"
      - "Postindustrial Context" by Fred Block, Postindustrial Possibilities, 1990
      - Public eye
        - "In Defense of Public Diplomacy" by Carnes Lord, Commentary, April 1984
        - "Is Democratic Theory for Export?" by Jacques Barzun, Ethics and International Affairs, 1987
        - "Iran-Contra Scandal and the 'Secret du Roi'" by Jonathan Dull, SHAFR Newsletter
        - James Madison, Public Opinion, December 19, 1791, Popular Basis of Political Authority
        - Printed matter
      - Records/writing
        - Charles Hill notes
        - Printed matter
      - Religious ethics.
      - Science.
        Table on Comparative Perspectives
      - "Science, Technology and the Western Miracle" by Nathan Rosenberg and L. E. Birdzell, Jr., Scientific American, November 1990
      - "Scientists vs. Captains of Erudition" by Thorstein Veblen
      - Security and cooperation in Europe.
      - Security decision-making
        - Domestic context
        - Topic 1 – Course introduction and overview
        - Topic 2 – American Constitutional System
        - Topic 3 – Separated Institutions Sharing Powers: The War Powers Resolution
        - Topic 4 – World of Washington, D.C.
        - Topic 5 – The Presidency (Box 89)
        - Topic 17 – Intelligence
        - Topic 18 – Intelligence
      - Sovereignty
        - "Beyond National Government" by Walter Lippmann, Early Writings, 1917
        - Column from New Yorker, December 26, 1988
        - "Who Cares About Rwanda?" by Lindsey Hilsum, Independent, May 29, 1994
        - "Declarations of Dependence?" by Peter Rodman, National Review, June 13, 1994
        - Sovereignty proposal, Institute of International Studies, 1992
        - "Sovereignty: An Institutional Perspective" by Stephen Krasner, Comparative Political Studies, April 1988
        - "Sovereignty and Interdependence: Britain's Place in the World" by Geoffrey Howe, International Affairs, 1990
        - Printed matter
      - Soviet Union
        - "To the Stalin Mausoleum" by Z, Daedalus, Winter 1990
        - Charles Hill notes
        - Outlines regarding the Soviet economy
      - Spain/Latin America
        - "New Spain and the New Latin America" by Howard Wiarda, World and I, December 1991
        - "Exploring Our Forgotten Century: Between Columbus and Jamestown" by Joseph Judge, National Geographic, March 1988
        - Article on Spain, Encyclopedia Britannica
      - Speechwriting
        - Charles Hill notes
        - "Effectiveness of Reagan's 'Star Wars' Address" by Robert Rowland and Rodger Payne, Political Communication and Persuasion, 1987
        - Ronald Reagan's address to the nation on "Defense and National Security,", March 23, 1983
        - Printed matter
      - Stanford University
        - Motto "Die Luft der Freiheit weht"
        - "Curricular Politics" by Sidney Hook, Partisan Review, undated
        - Printed matter on Stanford's Western Civilization/Great Book debate, 1991
        - Printed matter on the University and the World
        - Prospectus on the Stanford World Institute
        - Talking points for Stanford Trustees' Retreat, August 17, 1990
      - Statecraft (Box 90)
        - Charles Hill notes
        - "A Statecraft for the Future," draft, November 2, 1990
        - Printed matter
      - States. "Central Perspectives on the Modern State" by David Held, Idea of the Modern State, ed. by Gregor McLennan and others, 1984
      - Summit meetings
        - Charles Hill notes
        - Draft, Chapter 10
        - "Summit Fatigue" by Charles Hill, May 8, 1990
        - "Eisenhower's Reluctant Summit – Inside Geneva July 1955" by Francis Loewenheim, May 24, 1990
        - "Emotion and High Politics: Personal Relations at the Summit in Late Nineteenth-Century Britain and Germany" by Judith Hughes, 1983
        - Printed matter
      - Terrorism (opera).
      - Trade
        - Article on international trade, Encyclopedia Britannica, 1979
        - Chapter from International Trade and the Tokyo Round Negotiation by Gilbert Winham
        - Chapter from Rise of the Trading State by Richard Rosecrance
        - Part of a chapter entitled "Trading World"
        - Part of a chapter entitled "Force or Trade"
        - Chapter entitled "Toward the Future"
        - "From Geopolitics to Geo-Economics" by Edward Luttwak, National Interest, Summer 1990
        - Printed matter
      - Trust.
        Charles Hill notes
      - United States
        - Department of State. "Why Everyone Hates the State Department" by Elliott Abrams
        - Economic policy.
        - History. Chapter from Cycles of American History by Arthur Schlesinger, Jr., 1986
      - War (Box 91)
        - Art of war – Force and diplomacy (material to be used for an essay)
        - Cold War
        - Diplomacy
        - Justice and war
      - Withdrawal.
  - Biographical information (Box 30)
  - Correspondence, 1989-1993
  - Speeches and writings. Miscellaneous, 1988-1993
  - Subject file (Box 80)
    - China (material collected primarily when Charles Hill was Political Officer in Hong Kong, 1966-1969)
      - General – Printed matter in Chinese and English, including an atlas and maps
      - Agriculture
      - American advisers/missionaries
      - Cambodia
      - Chang I-su
      - Chen I
      - Ch'en Tsai-tao
      - Ch'i Yen-ming
      - Chiang Ch'ing
      - Chiang Hua
      - Chou En-lai
      - Chu Te
      - Communist Party (Box 81)
        - Leaders' speeches and public appearances, 1966
        - Leadership and purges
        - Ninth Congress, 1969
      - Counter-revolution trials, 1967
      - Cultural Revolution
        - undated
        - 1966
        - 1967 (Box 82)
        - 1968-1970 (Box 83)
      - Diplomatic Corps, 1966
      - Economic conditions
      - Foreign relations
        - undated
        - 1967
        - 1968
        - 1969
        - 1970
      - Foreign trade (Box 92)
      - Fu Ch'ung-pi
      - Government – Coup plans, February 1966
      - Government councils, 1949-1962
      - Ho Lung
      - Inner Mongolia
      - January revolution notes
      - Ko Ching-shih
      - Kuai Ta-fu
      - Kwangtung
      - Li Ta
      - Lin Li-ming
      - Lin Piao
      - Liu Shao-ch'i
      - Liu Shao-ch'i/Wang Kuang-mei
      - Lo Jui-ching
      - Mao Tse-tung
        - Interview with Edgar Snow
        - Quotations
      - Military policy
      - Mu Hsin
      - Nuclear weapons
      - Peng Chen
      - Peng Te-huai
      - People's Liberation Army (PLA) (Box 93)
      - Permanent revolution
      - Population, 1967-1968
      - Public health
      - Railroads
      - Red Guards
      - Revolutionary Committees, 1967-1968
      - Science conference, July 1966
      - Sino-Soviet border (Box 94-95)
      - Socialist Education Movement (Box 96)
      - Sun Yat-sen
      - T'an Chen-lin
      - Teng Hsiao-ping
      - Tibet
      - Tientsin
      - Tseng Hsi-sheng
      - Unequal treaties
      - Wang En-mao
      - Wang Li
      - Wu Teh
      - Yang Chen-wu
      - Yang Yung
      - Yao Ke
      - Yao Teng-shan
      - Yeh Chien-ying
      - List of names of public appearances by Chinese leaders, August 18 - October 18, 1966 (scroll)
      - Card files (Box 97-98)
    - East Asia (Box 99)
    - Herodotus
    - History
    - Hong Kong
    - Institute of Nautical Archaeology
    - James, Henry
    - Middle East – Riverbed project
    - Miscellany
    - Pragmatism
    - Reagan Administration – Geneva Summit meeting between President Ronald Reagan and General Secretary Mikhail Gorbachev, November 1985
    - Soviet Union – Foreign relations - Asia
    - Stanford University – Institute for International Studies (IIS) (Box 100)
    - Statecraft
    - Strategic Defense Initiative/Anti-Ballistic Missiles (SDI/ABM) (Box 101)
    - Taiwan – Foreign relations
    - United Nations studies, Yale University
    - United States - Foreign relations – China/Hong Kong/Taiwan
  - Audio-visual file (Box 102)
    - Videotape and transcript of Charles Hill appearance on the television show Uncommon Knowledge, October 17, 1998
    - Phonotape of Charles Hill remarks, Commonwealth Club of California, San Francisco, July 8, 1994
    - Two photographs of fighting in Vietnam, 1972
    - Wall poster in Chinese, 1968
    - Two microfilms, 1966-1967 (Box 103)
  - Subject file – United Nations. (Box 104)
    See also Boxes 114-115
    Manuscript of UNvanquished: The United States versus the United Nations, 1999, by Boutros Boutros-Ghali.
  - Biographical file – Memberships (Yale University. Grand Order of the Golden Bulldog) (Box 105)
  - Correspondence - Sorley, Lewis, 1999
  - Speeches and writings
    - "Clinton's Conduct of Foreign Policy: A Dangerous Legacy" Handwritten draft
    - "High Altitude, Stealth and Cruise Missile Warfare," outline, July 13, 1996
    - Letter to the editor regarding the review by Jeffrey Record of A Better War by Lewis Sorley, New York Times Book Review, July 4, 1999
    - Notes for a memorandum written in 1962, after the Cuban Missile Crisis, arguing in favor of a test ban treaty, which the United States government then pursued and signed with the U.S.S.R. in 1963.
      This memo was written during Hill's first assignment in the State Department
    - "U.S. and U.N.: Time to Stop the Scapegoating and Start Cooperating to Stop Ethnic Strife"
    - "U.S. China Policy at Present," handwritten notes, typescript, July 26
    - "Warren Christopher's In the Stream of History," review essay, Political Science Quarterly, Summer
  - Subject file
    - Bunker, Ellsworth. Copy of material from the John F. Kennedy Library related to Bunker's mediation on Yemen, 1963
    - Jovin, Suzanne.
      Printed matter about her murder at Yale University, December 4, 1998
    - Middle East - Israeli-Palestinian Peace Process, "Riverbed"
    - Shultz, George. Draft of article by Walter LaFeber, "Technology and U.S. Foreign Policy" wherein George Shultz, William Seward, and Elihu Root are cited as the three Secretaries of State who were in office during times of technological advances and how they reacted; correspondence with Charles Hill, July
    - United Nations.
      Copy of correspondence and printed matter
- Increment received in 2002 (Box 106)
  - Biographical file
    - Biographical sketches
    - Board membership - Maxtor Corporation
    - Clippings
    - Family
    - Honorary degree - Glassboro State College
    - Legal cases
    - Stanford trip – Bombay to Cairo
    - U.S. Department of State
    - Yale University
  - Correspondence, 1963-2002
    - General, 1988-2001
    - General (Box 107)
    - Aime, Jean-Claude, 1993-2000
    - Berry, Ryan, 1999-2001
    - Boutros-Ghali, Boutros, 1992-2001
    - Conquest, Robert, 1999
    - Dam, Kenneth, 2001
    - Doherty, William, 1998-2001
    - Dorfman, Toni, 2000
    - Epstein, Jason, 1998
    - Ewing, Elizabeth, 1993-2000
    - Gottlieb, Gidon, 1998-2001
    - Greensboro College, 1998-1999
    - Henriksen, Thomas, 1993-1999
    - Hill, Katie, 1984-2000
    - Hill, M. C., 1984-1994
    - Hill, Martha, 1963-undated
    - Hsieh, Wayne, 2000-2001 (Box 108)
    - Kennedy, Paul, 1993-2002
    - Kristol, William, 1996
    - Lafeber, Walter, 1993-1999
    - Lombardo, Caroline, 1997-2000
    - Lyman, Richard, 1998
    - Nadaner, Jeffrey, 1997-2001
    - Park, C.S., 1998-2001
    - Raisian, John, 1993-1998
    - Reed, Joseph Verner, 1997-2001
    - Safire, William, 1993-1998
    - Shultz, George, 1988-2002
    - Sicherman, Harvey, 1989-2001
    - Skinner, Kiron, 1994-2000
    - Smith, Gaddis, 1993-1998
    - Smith, George, 1997-2001
    - Thompson, Norma, undated-2001
    - Van Lieu, Emily, 1998-2000
    - Wood, Allen, undated
  - Speeches and writings (Box 109)
    - General
      - Activity report
      - Books on Vietnam
      - Course for Polish/Hungarian diplomats
      - Drafts for
        - Boutros Boutros-Ghali.
          See also Boxes 104 and 114-115
        - George Shultz
        - Norma Thompson
      - Editing, including biography of Ellsworth Bunker
      - Letters to the editor
      - Notes
      - Panel on The Age of Terror
      - Review of In the Stream of History by Warren Christopher
      - Talking points, notes - Riverbed negotiation
    - undated
      - "Burke"
      - "Elements for an Intermediate Agreement in Jerusalem"
      - "From 'Rogues' to Rivals"
      - "Ship of State"
      - "Sovereignty and Security"
      - "Tocqueville"
      - "U.S. and the U.N."
      - "Woman: The Core Text"
    - 1970
      - "Indochina Story"
    - 1990
      - "Man Thinking"
    - 1993
      - "Notes for a New Foreign Policy"
    - 1994
      - "Twin Peaks as Whitewater"
    - 1995
      - "Civilization and Its Malcontents"
      - "Connections"
      - "Connections" (Box 110)
    - 1997
      - "NATO Strategy for a New Generation"
    - 1998
      - "Instilling Ethics" – Introduction
      - "On Clinton"
      - "Ten Recommendments"
    - 1999
      - "Herodotus on War"
      - "Wye II Has Opened the Door to Peace in the Middle East"
    - 2000
      - "Europeanization of America"
      - "Future of the United Nations"
    - 2001
      - "Creating Collateral Advantage: The Positive Side of the War on Terrorism"
      - "Middle East"
      - "Religion: Why Is It Good for America when It Causes Conflict Elsewhere?"
      - "Should America Continue to Promote Democracy Abroad?"
      - "Skill Set"
      - "Vietnam: Go Tell the Spartans"
      - "War and National Character"
    - 2002
      - "Crisis in the Middle East: Making the Most of the Moment"
      - "Emerson"
      - "Hercules New Labors"
      - "Nationalism"
  - Subject file
    - Afghanistan – U.S.-U.S.S.R. agreement
    - Burma
    - Bush Administration foreign policy
    - Comprehensive Nuclear Test Ban Treaty
    - Dole, Robert – Presidential Campaign, 1996
    - Eban, Abba (Box 112)
    - Festival of Arts
    - Hoover Institution
    - Hoover/Stanford ideas
    - Islamic challenge in the Middle East
    - Kissinger, Henry
    - Liberal education
    - Middle East
    - Miscellany
    - North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO) (Box 113)
    - Reagan, Ronald
    - Shultz, George
    - Solzhenitsyn, Aleksandr
    - United Nations
      - General
      - Agenda for Development (draft)
      - Chart – Aid to thought
    - Yale University
      - General
      - Berkeley College
      - Continuing Council (Carnegie)
      - Directed Studies lecture
      - Grand Strategy Conference
      - International Studies
      - Mace and Chain
  - Notebook on the Middle East (in original order) (Box 111)
    - European Ambassadors – Non-NATO, March 17, 1979
    - Map of the Strait of Tiran
    - Map of Israel and adjacent occupied territories, February 15, 1969
    - Map of Israeli settlements in the West Bank, World Zionist Organization, "The Hope by 1983"
    - Arab-Israeli/outstanding issues, February 23, 1979
    - Map of Jordan Valley water diversion projects
    - Israel – Department of State Background Notes, April 1979
    - "Key Dates in Mideast Peace Quest"
    - Excerpt of U.S. government communication on the Middle East
    - Middle East checklist
    - USINFO from Washington to Tel Aviv, September 20, 1979.
      Interview with Secretary of State Cyrus Vance to be published in Maariv
    - "Costs of War in the Middle East," draft, April 20, 1979
    - Article from Ha'aretz on Israel's isolation, June 15, 1979
    - Excerpt of paper on U.N. Security Council Resolution 242
    - Text of Egypt's New Peace Plan, July 5, 1978
    - Text of U. N. Resolution 242 on Principles for a Middle East Settlement, November 22, 1967
    - Statement by Jimmy Carter, March 13, 1979
    - Texts of the letters accompanying Camp David Agreements, September 1978
    - Text of Camp David Agreements, September 17, 1978
    - "Vienna Document,", July 10, 1978
    - Anwar as-Sadat's Salzburg Document, July 14, 1978
    - Moshe Dayan briefing, July 25, 1978
    - List of Middle East negotiating positions, (AIPAC), August 1978
    - Opposition to the Camp David Agreements (illegible in places)
    - Camp David, "What Israel Has Conceded,", September 1978
    - Map of Jewish settlements in Gaza Strip and Sinai
    - United Nations Emergency Force (under Sinai II), holograph by Charles Hill, August 5, 1978
    - Map of UNIFIL deployment as of January 1979
    - United States assistance to Israel, November 1, 1977; April 1978; November 1978
    - U.S. arms aid for Israel, May 25, 1978
    - Chart of the location of Palestinians
    - "Palestinian Guerrillas"
    - Middle East population, 1978; Palestinian refugees
    - "Texts of Israeli Plans for West Bank and Sinai," Washington Post, December 29, 1977
    - Maps
      - 2 maps of Israeli settlements, West Bank
      - 6 maps of Israel